[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is priyanka raghavan
for software engineering radio today
listeners will be treated to the topic
data observability
and to lead us through this we have with
us
our guest
kevin who who is the co-founder and ceo
at metaplane
it's a data observability startup which
focuses on helping teams find and fix
data quality problems
prior to this he researched intersection
of machine learning and data science at
mit
where he earned a phd kevin has written
many articles on data observability in a
variety of popular as well as scientific
publications so welcome to the show
kevin such a pleasure to talk with you
today i'm a longtime listener of sc
radio and everyone on my team also is a
listener so hopefully i can make them
proud today for such a pleasure to be
here great
is there anything else you would like
listeners to know about yourself before
we get into the show i think you did a
great job with the introduction and
we'll touch on this during the show but
i would love to start by saying
data teams have so much to learn from
software teams
that if you have a data team at your
company
chances are that a lot of the best
practices that you have developed as an
engineer could also help them deploy
more effective and more resilient data
for your stakeholders internally
so let's jump into observability and
some definitions before we get into data
observability
the first thing i wanted to ask you is
something basic but let's start from the
top how would you define observability
in your words
observability is the degree of
visibility you have into your system
and that is
the colloquial definition that we use in
data observability and what software
observability devops observability tools
like data dog and signalfx and splunk
have developed
and it really descends from the physical
science discipline of control theory
where
there was a concept called the
controllability of a system that given
the inputs can you manipulate and
understand the state of that system
well the mathematical dual the
corresponding concept is
given the output of a system can you
infer the state of that system
so that is the rigorous definition from
which our more colloquial definition is
derived
why do you think it is necessary to
have a view of the system a centralized
view which everyone seems to be striving
towards
why is that necessary
it's necessary because
systems are complicated
that
as
software engineers we
have so many systems working
independently of each other
interacting with each other
that when something goes wrong which
inevitably will
it's very very time consuming to
understand what the implications
of that incident might be and what the
root cause might be
and because it's difficult to understand
it costs a lot of time for you
a time that is hard to get back
and it costs trust in the people who
rely on the systems that you develop so
let's go back 10 years ago or 20 years
ago when it was more common to deploy
software systems without any sort of
telemetry make a rails app put on an ec2
box put a heartbeat check there and call
it a day and i say everyone did this but
a lot of people did do this
the only way that you knew that
something went wrong in your system was
degraded or broken performance for your
users
and that is not acceptable and over the
past decade
with the rise of tools like datadog
we have the visibility so that your team
can be proactive and get ahead of
breakages that's why it's important is
because it helps you stay proactive and
maintain a lot of trust in your system
i'd like to revisit the
physics definition that you gave to the
first answer
so we have this term entropy in physics
which has pretty close connection to
control theory information theory
what i was wondering is how the
uncertainty of an outcome
how does that relate to observability
great question and observability has
very deep roots in physics we'll talk
about entropy but we can go into the
other route in just a second but entropy
is
the measure of the amount of information
in a system
at least in the information theoretic
definition it is the number of bits in
other words the number of yes or no
questions that must be answered for you
to fully understand the system
so in a very simple system for example
a gas at thermal equilibrium in a box
you don't need many yes or no questions
to fully describe that system
when it becomes more dynamic right when
it starts turning into like your
software infrastructure you actually
need many yes or no answers
to understand fully the state of that
system
which one is part of the reason why
observability is important is because
our systems tend to become more in
traffic over time it's almost like the
second law of thermodynamics where
entropy only increases that that also
applies to man-made systems unless
you're kind of pulling it back in case
you have that one person on your team
who is a real stickler for refactoring
that and as systems become more and more
entropic the surface area of breakage
increases
and
that's why you need observability or at
least some increased degree of
visibility is to fight against the
forces of entropy
and not all of is under your control or
your fault either on a data team right
for example if you centralize a lot of
data in a analytic data store like
snowflake
you can be very disciplined about the
data sets that you create
but if you open that up to your end
users and they start using a business
intelligence tool like looker
they can start
exploding the number of dependencies on
your system so that's entropy can emerge
in many different forms
but i love the fact that you brought
that up because
to go to observability and its roots in
control theory
believe it or not this takes us all the
way back to the 17th century i believe
where christian higgins he was a dutch
physicist a contemporary of isaac newton
he discovered saturn's rings
he created this device that he was from
the netherlands and the netherlands are
famous for windmills
the problem with windmills
which were used at the time to grind
grain
is that
there's an optimal speed at which the
millstone rotates to grind grain into
like the right shape and size but wind
is variable speed all right you can't
control the speed of the wind
but
hagen's developed this device called the
centrifugal governor
which is almost like an ice skater
that
when they bring out their arms they slow
down
and then when they bring in their arms
they speed up it's the same concept but
applied to like a physical system
where
now using this device the speed of the
millstone is much more controlled but
fast forward a few hundred years
james clerk maxwell who many of your
listeners may know is the father of
electromagnetism right maxwell's
equations the
the four equations that govern them all
he developed control theory
to describe how a centrifugal governor
works
he was trying to understand okay like
given the inputs into this spinning
machine
what are the dynamics of that machine
and vice versa from observability
and that's really the lineage that we
trace down all the way to today where
ultimately you have these highly complex
systems that we want to understand in
simpler terms right highly entropic but
give us something that we can actually
use to summarize
the system and that's where the
three pillars of software observability
come in we've heard of metrics traces
and logs
with these three you can understand
arbitrarily the state of a software
system at any point in time
and also where the four pillars of data
observability come into play as well
in episode 455 we did talk about
software telemetry and in fact they
talked about these traces logs and
metrics under an umbrella terminal which
is software observability telemetry
in data observability you told me about
four pillars
what is that could you just briefly
touch upon that
for sure well before that even though
data is ultimately produced by either a
human interacting with a machine or a
machine producing data and that's
manipulated and presented through other
machines that
data does have critical differences from
the software world
there are some properties
that make it so that we can't take the
concepts wholesale we have to rather use
them as inspiration
with that in mind the way that we
think of the four pillars of data
observability is okay priyanka if you
describe the company you work at like
what is the data you might say okay
well if i have a table in the database i
can describe
like
here's a distribution like for example
the distribution of the number of sales
right
this number has like a certain mean
value this min and max and that here's a
list of a bunch of
customers right
here the regions they're from right the
number of regions like which columns
have pii and these sorts of descriptive
measures are what we call metrics right
they're metrics about your data
then you might also say like this
customers table
these are the columns and the column
types that's schema this is the last
time it was updated the frequency with
which it's updated the number of rows
we call this metadata like external
metadata and the reason we draw a
distinction between these two is because
you can change the internal metrics
without changing the external metadata
and vice versa
where like the cells can change we don't
necessarily need more rows but if the
schema changes it doesn't necessarily
change the statistical properties
but then
you might say okay but this is one table
data is all connected to each other
that ultimately going back to the
sources is a human putting a number into
your machine or it is a machine
producing some data and everything
derives from some operation applied to
those ultimate sources or some derived
table thereof and that is called lineage
and that's a pretty unique property to
the data world
where
the data comes from somewhere right
at multiple levels of resolution so to
speak where you can say this table
is the result of joining these two
parent tables or this
column is the result of this operation
applied to two parent tables or even
like this
one data point
is the result of
another operation so it's important to
try the lineage over time and lastly
it's important to understand the
relationships between your data and
external world
where
your company you might be using a tool
like five tran or error byte to pull
data from an application like salesforce
into your database and ultimately your
data might be consumed by like an
operations analyst who wants to
understand what's the state of my
process currently
and data is ultimately
meant to be used so and logs kinds of
encodes that information so to back up a
little bit you have
two pillars describing the data itself
metrics and metadata and two pillars
describing relationships
lineage and logs
great this is fantastic
but before i dive deep into each of
these
areas
i want you to tell me about
say the similarities between data and
software
observability so listening to what you
just said
i can understand that
the similarities that it lets you get to
the root cause of an issue is there
anything else
the biggest similarity you're totally
right is the job to be done
that one of the major use cases of an
observability tool is incident
management
to tell you
when something potentially bad has
occurred and to give you the information
you need to both
identify the root cause
like you mentioned and identify the
potential impact
in the software world you might use
traces right like
time correlated or request scoped logs
and in the data world you might use
lineage so it does the same job there
and
ultimately it's for the same
overarching purpose which is to save you
time and to increase trust in your
system if there was one thing that you
could say which is the difference
between
data and software observability is it
this thing with the lineage that you
talk about is that the difference or are
there more things
there are more things
just to go down some of the more common
differences that we've seen
there's a common saying that you should
treat your software like
cattle and not pets
and you know i don't condone treating
cattle necessarily but basically treat
your software as interchangeable
that if something isn't working right
treat it as ephemeral treat it you know
as stateless as possible just like take
it down spin it back up you can't do
that in the data world
where if your etl process is broken you
can't just you know spit it down and
spin it back up and now everything is
fine because now you have bad data in
your system or missing data in your
system so you have to backfill
everything that is bad or missing so
that i would consider data not like
cattle but more like
thoroughbred race horses where the
lineage really matters you can't just
kill it but you have to really trace
everything that's been going on and one
corollary of the fact that
data has
like these lingering consequences is
that like if there's a data incident
the impact negative impact compounds
over time
right every second that passes
the amount of bad data or missing data
goes up and up and up
it's so critical to
minimize the time to identify and time
to resolve issues
in the data world of course it's very
like
case dependent depends on how data is
used but i think that's one really
critical difference and another
difference is
the absence of playbooks in the data
world so as engineers we have playbooks
to diagnose and fix issues
but
in the data team there are none
that if there's a bug that occurs you
get like some duplicate rows it affects
your churn and then everything breaks
from there
that's something that we want to change
with introducing data observability and
something that we think will change
but we're not quite there yet
so those are the things that you can
learn from the software observability
space that is how can you self heal i
guess is what you're saying i guess what
i'm not very clear about is if there is
a missing data where you said you had to
go back in time and you know try to
figure out what happened and how to get
back how do you do that how do you fill
in missing data
interpolation might be an answer in
certain cases and i think it really
depends
like the number of ways that data can go
wrong is you know similar to the number
of ways that software can go wrong
there's an infinite number right it's
the whole total story core about all
happy families are the same all unhappy
families aren't happy in a different way
so if you do have missing data for
example
because
your etl process failed for a day
and one way to fix that hopefully is if
salesforce has their own system of
record and has that data still existing
where you can that's like spin it back
up and extend the window that you're
replicating into your database and you
can call it a
if in another situation you have
streaming data let's say your users are
using segment and that is being popped
into your data warehouse or you know you
have a kafka stream like an event stream
and then it goes down for a day
that you might have to do some
interpolation because you're not going
to get that data back unless some other
system is storing it for you so it's
really case dependent which is why it's
so important to have this root cause
analysis
one last question i want to ask before
we deep dive into the pillars is is
there a rule of thumb on how many
metrics you should collect to analyze
the data the reason i ask that is
because in software observability also
we find if you have too many metrics
it's mind boggling
and then you forget what you're looking
for
because you're just overwhelmed by the
metrics so is there a rule of thumb that
typically data engineers should have
only so many or
is there no limit on that
i think the industry is still trying to
arrive at the right level i personally
like reverse engineering from
the number of alerts that
you
as a data observability user get into
your you know whatever channel like
slack or email or page or duty
where
that's ultimately what matters
is
what does a tool
draw your attention to and behind the
scenes it doesn't matter so much how
many metrics or pieces of metadata are
being tracked over time
and we found that it depends on the size
of the team but a nice sweet spot might
be anywhere between three to seven
alerts per day at max
once it goes beyond that then you just
start with like tuning it out right like
your slack channel is already going
crazy
anything above and beyond like a handful
a day is too much
now
to go back to your question like what
does that mean
for
the number of metrics that you track
it means that
we have to
have a nice like compromise between
tracking as much as we can because
like we mentioned before like the
surface area is key anything can go
wrong especially when there's so many
dependencies that we want to track
at least the freshness and the volume
of every table that you have if feasible
that also means that if we do track
everything that our models have to be
really on point any anomaly detection
cannot over alert you and the ui needs
to be able to synthesize all the alerts
in a way that isn't overwhelming and
just gives you what you need at that
point in time to make a decision about
triage essentially like is this worth my
time
so that's where
the quality of the tool
comes in and it doesn't have to be of
course a commercial toy it could also be
something that you build internally or
open source but that's where a lot of
the finesse comes in
i think that is a very good answer
because i think the tooling also helps
in fine-tuning your way of looking at
things and maybe your focus areas is
very
right i just wanted to draw the analogy
to like a security tools where ideally
your vulnerability scanner scans
everything right it scans the whole
service area of your api but doesn't cry
wolf too many times it doesn't send you
too many false positives so it's the
same balance there it's a good analogy
that yeah the false positive is not like
through the roof because that's also
something that you work with right you
also tune the tool to say hey this is
really a false positive so don't show up
next time so then your alerts also get a
little better because you work with it
over time
for sure and thankfully we don't work in
a space that is like cancer diagnosis or
self-driving cars
where false positives in our world are
okay you just can't have too many of
them and you want to make sure that
users right engineers who are actually
doing the work
feel like their agency and time is being
respected
so if you're gonna send me a false alert
at least make it something that's
reasonable that
i can give good feedback into you and
then you can learn from that over time
you're totally right
great so maybe now we can just deep dive
into the pillars of the data
observability so the first two things i
want to talk about is where you talked
about metadata which is the data about
the data can you explain that give me
some examples and
how you would use that for observability
the most foundational tests
do describe the external characteristics
of data
for example the number of rows
i.e like the volume test the schema and
the freshness
and the reason this is important is
because it is the most tied to
the
end user value
so to give you an example oftentimes
when people use data there is like some
time sensitivity of it
where if your
cfo is looking at a dashboard and it is
one week behind it doesn't matter if the
data was correct last week we needed to
be correct today
and that's actually a great example of
the most common issue that metaplane and
everyday observability tool helps
identify which is freshness issues right
time is of the essence here
where it's all relative to the task at
hand but you need to make sure that it
is within a tolerable bond right if you
need it to be real time
ensure that it's real time if you need
to be fresh up to you a week ensure
that's fresh up to a week
and
the second most common issue that we
find are schema changes where when we
write sql when we create tools
there's some assumption that the schema
is consistent atom means schema just in
terms of the number of like the columns
and the tables and their names and types
but even like within
a column right
what are the enums what you would expect
and
because there's so many dependencies
like when an upstream schema changes
things can really really break and this
can happen through
salesforce updating its schema or
a product engineer changing the name of
an event in amplitude for example which
i've definitely done and it's not
intentional that you break downstream
systems but it's hard to know if you
don't know what the impact is
and the third category of this sort of
external metadata
is the volume and you'd be very
surprised how frequently this comes up
for a whole variety of reasons where
a table you'd expect it to grow at a
million rows a day and then suddenly you
get 100 000 rows
one this is a good example of a silent
data bug as we like to call it where
how the heck would you have known
no one's checking this table all the
time
and it is very difficult to know
both that that occurred and what the
potential impact of it is
there's a whole universe of root causes
but this happens quite a bit in
production systems
i had read in a lot of blogs and see
literature about the dimensions of the
metadata i think they talked about
timeliness so would you group
these characteristics of the data
together and then that's what you track
great point about the dimensions of
metadata the
really data observability descends
from information quality research like
in tandem with software observability
but there's a huge amazing literature
from the 1990s and 2000s from pioneers
like richard wang and diane strong
that describe what does it mean to have
high quality data
and they've identified
like you mentioned many dimensions of
data quality
such as like the timeliness of the data
of referential integrity
and they also
have identified
like a nice taxonomy with which you can
think about
all these dimensions and metrics so just
a step back a little bit there are
dimensions of data quality which are
really like categories of why things are
important
like timeliness
as a dimension
really answers why
timing is important like why is the data
in my warehouse not up to date right why
does my dashboard take so long to
refresh but once you decide to measure
that dimension then it becomes a metric
where
if your data is not up to date you might
measure
the lag between when your dashboard was
last accessed and when your data was
last refreshed or when your dashboard is
taking a long time to refresh you might
understand like the latency between your
etl process and when that dashboard is
actually being materialized or the
underlying data is being materialized
so it's like
high level concept and then how it's
actually measured and there's a whole
list like a huge list of these
dimensions and measures over time now
you can think of is the data accurate
does it actually describe the real world
is the data internally consistent
not only does it satisfy referential
integrity but that you can't pick data
out of one table and out of another
table and that they result in two
different numbers
and is it complete
right does every piece of data that we
expect to exist
actually exist these are what we think
of as intrinsic dimensions of data
quality
where
even if the data is not being used you
can still measure
the accuracy and completeness and
consistency and it still matters but
that's in contrast with the extrinsic
dimensions
where
you need to start from a task
that the data helps drive right
and some extrinsic dimensions might
include like is the data
reliable
do you your user is like regarded as
true and that's related to how timely
the data is like you mentioned before
and is irrelevant at all right you can
have
a lot of data for
like a product
use case but if you really need to use
it for a sales use case it doesn't
really matter if it was good and that is
considered part of data quality
okay interesting the relevance of the
data that is an important factor yeah
that makes a lot of sense which is
something i think which
yeah i guess maybe even software
observability can learn from data
observability
yeah it's really a two-way street
because ultimately they're two different
roles they do two different things
i do think yeah the data quality
research is like very
thorough and then now it's really coming
to fruition because data is increasingly
used for like
critical use cases right if your
reporting dashboard is down for a day
sometimes that's okay but if it's being
used to train
machine learning models that impact a
customer's experience or decide how you
allocate ad spend for example
that can be costly
we talked about timeliness and relevance
of the data
i also want to know about in software
observability when we log data
we have this concept that we really need
to be careful about pii and private data
and things like that
and i'm assuming that's even more so in
data observability i was thinking about
this netflix documentary we watched and
you know we're collecting data and that
contributes to bias and things like that
does that play into data observability
also can you talk a little bit about
that there's yet another field that's
emerging called machine learning
observability which kind of picks up
where data observability stops
so
frequently a data observability tool
might go up into like the features right
the input features to
train
a machine learning model
but unless you're storing like model
performance
and characteristics about the features
within the warehouse that's kind of as
far as it can go but there's a whole
category of tools emerging to understand
the performance of machine learning
models over time
both
in terms of how the training performance
departs from the test performance but
also to understand
important qualities like bias
and
that is definitely a part of data
quality right sometimes bias
can be introduced because
the data is simply not correct in some
dimension right maybe it's not timely
maybe it's not relevant maybe it was
transformed incorrectly
but data can also be incorrect
for
non-technical reasons and by that i mean
the data in the warehouse and being used
by your model can be fully technically
correct and yet if it
doesn't satisfy some important
assumptions
about the real world
then it still can like not be a very
high quality data set or a high quality
model as a result and there's a lot of
great work
including work by a great friend of mine
joy bolinwini on algorithmic bias and
shout out to the algorithmic justice
league
where
facial recognition
is
increasingly deployed in the world right
both in public settings and in private
settings right you look at your iphone
or you have to submit something to the
irs thankfully she find the end to that
but let's just say that these algorithms
don't work as well for
everyone right and ideally if something
is rolled out at such a scale we want it
to work as well for one group as it does
for another
so that is 100 a part of data quality
and a good example of how data quality
isn't just the quality of the data in
your warehouse it goes all the way back
to how it's even being collected that's
very interesting and that got me
thinking about this other point could
there be a scenario when if someone
maliciously modifies the data is that
something that also the tool can pick up
or like something built into the
framework
for tools
if it affects uh
underlying distribution
then
a tool like ours would be able to
detect when that distribution changes
drastically
but oftentimes it's more subtle than
that like these sorts of adversarial
data poisoning attacks
which
small changes into the input features
have drastic changes to the behavior of
the model at least in like certain edge
cases
oftentimes it's very difficult to detect
and i know that there's a lot of great
academic research
trying to address this problem
i don't want to overstay our
capabilities or like the state of the
art and industry today but
i'd be skeptical that we'd be able to
catch everything just like some of the
most impactful attacks
okay so it is probably in the infancy
stage and where there's a lot more
research happening in this area is what
you're saying exactly
also in terms of this data observability
let's talk about the other aspect right
we've talked about data quality a little
bit about the metrics and the metadata
and also let's talk more about the logs
which is directly the data software
observability when you look at the logs
it's how the interaction between two
systems
in data observability i was reading that
it also captures the interaction between
humans in the system right uh
can you tell us how that is
whether it is a sales rep and putting
the contract size of a deal or it is a
customer inputting their mps score
or interacting with your site like data
comes from people
when it doesn't come from a machine
and there's humans that touch data all
the way along the value chain or the
life cycle of data within a company from
the data collection
to
the
etl system that was manually triggered
for example to pull it into a data
warehouse to the data team writing
transformation scripts for example in
dbt to transform it from a raw table to
a metric that
is actually relevant to the end user
and then
it's also consumed by humans at the end
right whether it's looking at a business
intelligence tool
liquor or tableau to see how these
numbers that ultimately aggregated
numbers change over time it could be
sent back into salesforce to help a
sales rep make a decision
that along every step of the process is
a human involved and the reason that's
important
is to understand the impact
so for example if
a table
goes down for a day
does that matter
if it's not used by anyone it doesn't
really matter but if it's being used by
the cfo that day at the board meeting
you you better bet that it's important
that the table is up and fresh and it's
you know the data doesn't tell you this
right you need to have aggregated log
data to understand
what the downstream impact is
as well as what the root cause might be
i know i'm a broken record about the
downstream impact and the upstream root
cause but that's what it always comes
back to right like
just hearing about an incident okay
that's useful but
it's the what's next that's important
and the root cause
like let's say that the table is not
fresh again
what could it possibly be maybe a
colleague on the data team merged in a
poor pr
that broke
an upstream table that
your current table depends on well it's
important to know
who merged that pr and what the context
around that decision was
maybe
there was an invalid input in a source
system some put a negative value for a
sales number and it somehow violated
some assumption along the way it's
important to know what that was too
because
ultimately yes you are trying to solve
the issue at hand
but you also want to prevent it from
happening in the future and unless you
have like a real diagnosed root cause
it's difficult to do that and because
people are involved every step of the
way you need that information
so this is what ties into what you call
about the lineage of the data as well as
the relationship of the data right
exactly like let's be super concrete now
like this is a table that ultimately
describes the churn rate of your
customers for example
there are so many
dependencies of that table
whether it's the media dependencies like
the number of renewals versus the number
of churns over time but then you go one
level above that what impacts the number
of renewals well as a number of
customers that you have at all
and maybe some event or some
classification about whether or not they
turn but who determines what a customer
is maybe that's
a combination of the data in salesforce
with the data that you have in your
transactional database oh but who
determines a customer in salesforce is a
someone that has already submitted a
contract or someone that has you know
made a booking
reality is surprisingly detailed and i
know that there is a hacker news post
from a few years ago saying like as you
zoom in there's more and more to
discover
that is
as true in data as it is everywhere else
like there's assumptions there's turtles
all the way down
and let me give you two worlds for a
second where you have that customer
churn rate table
if it goes down and you don't have
lineage what do you do
well
what people do today is that they rely
on
their tribal knowledge
like they might have oh like i i know
that this is what the parent tables and
these are the assumptions that are in
place so let me check those out oh but
shoot or maybe i forgot something here
and
i know that colleague is working at this
other upstream table let me loop them in
for a second there's a lot of guesswork
very time consuming
and the holy grail is for you to have
that whole map
there for you and for you to not have to
maintain it
personally i don't think it's possible
to become 100 correct there but
oftentimes you don't need to be 100
correct you just need to be helpful
and that's why lineage is important
because it helps you answer those yes no
questions very very quickly
okay that's interesting i think it also
makes it kind of clear to me on why that
is important to find out the root cause
and the impact as you see the two
major things that we talked about in
this chunk
why that are my tombstone
my birthday the recause
whatever the year i die that's the
impact
this is great so let's just move on to
maybe some of the
tooling around this data observability
so
can't you do all of this in datadog
you can but it'd be hard we use datadog
internally first of all
i spend a lot of my day in datadog and
it is an amazing tool
but as
software engineers we know the
importance of having the right
integrations the right abstractions and
the right workflows in place
that
you can stretch datadog to do this
and for instance you're monitoring the
mean of a column in a table
but let's say that you want to monitor
the freshness of every table in your
database
that starts becoming a little bit tricky
right and time consuming you can do it
i'm confident that the listeners of this
podcast will be able to do that
but it's much easier when a tool kind of
does that for you and let's say that you
want to understand the bi impact right
integrate with liquor or tableau or mode
or sigma to understand
the lineage
of this table downstream
as far as i can tell datadog does not
support those integrations maybe you can
write a custom integration and again
every listener here can do that do you
really want to do that
like let someone take care of that for
you
and lastly the workflows
like this process of identifying and
triaging
and finally resolving
these data quality issues have
a somewhat particular workflow it kind
of varies by team because like like we
said there are no playbooks but that's
something that data observability tools
also help with
so my answer is yes you can do it
but personally i don't think you should
want to do it if i were to like rephrase
that question and ask you what
would be the key components that a data
engineer should look for when they try
to pick a data observability tool what
would you say
integrations is number one if it doesn't
integrate with the tools that you have
don't bother right it's not worth your
time
thankfully a lot of teams are
centralizing on a common set of tools
like snowflake and data bricks for
example but
end-to-end coverage is really important
here so if it doesn't support what you
care about
don't bother and i also think
that
if it doesn't support the types of tests
that you're concerned with like no one
knows
your company's data better than you do
as a data engineer
and you know the last few times that
there are issues you know what those
issues were and if a tool that you're
evaluating or
even considering building
doesn't support the issues that have
happened and you think will happen
probably not worth your time either
and the last thing
is how much time how much investment is
required from you
and
i mean that out of total respect
where
engineers have so much on their plates
right like even putting work aside right
work might not be the number one two or
three thing on your to-do list it might
be i need to pay my mortgage i need to
take care of my parents or take care of
my kids and then work is somewhere on
that list and the number one thing on
those work list maybe i need to shoot
deliver this data to a stakeholder i
need to work on hiring
very far down that list might be
observability
so i think it's very important for a
tool to
be as easy to implement and easy to
maintain as possible
because
vendors like me can go and shout about
the importance of data observability all
day but ultimately it has to help your
life
so the learning curve should be very
easy is what you're saying also one of
the big factors for picking a tool
learning curve implementation
maintainability extensibility all of
these are important
let's come on to meta plane what what
does your tool do for data observability
apart from the mission statement which
i've seen but can you tell us on these
things like you have the integrations i
guess i'm guessing that's something that
you concentrate on
yeah metaplane
we call the datadog for data to be cute
but it plugs into your databases
like
snowflake and transactional databases
like postgres plugs into data
transformation tools like dbt
plugs into
downstream bi tools like liquor
and we
blanket your database with tests and
automatically
create anomaly detection models that
alert you when something might be going
wrong for example freshness or schema or
volume changes and then we give you the
downstream potential impact and the
upstream potential of your causes
your tools also do they work on the same
like you know software as a service kind
of thing is that the same model
it is the same model where
teams
generally implement metaplane in less
than 10 minutes
they provision the right roles and users
and
plug in their credentials
and then we just start monitoring for
them automatically
and after a certain training period then
we start sending alerts to the
destinations that they care about
i have to ask you this question it's not
only for metaplane but generally for any
data observability to you are collecting
a lot of data so one of the things we've
seen with also the software
observability tool is then suddenly
people say please ramp down the data
there's this huge cost
this is big bill that we paid so then we
have to like sort of reduce the logging
is that something that you help with as
well like through these data
observability tools do they also help
you with reducing your cost while also
logging enough to know about the root
cause and
impact well we'll say until the day we
die yeah exactly ultimately we don't
think that data absorbability should
cost more than your data
in the same way that data should not
should probably not cost more than your
aws bill
and as a result we try and
really minimize
the amount of time that we spend
quarrying your database
both the overhead that
you incur by bringing on an
observability tool and to make a pricing
and packaging model that makes sense for
teams
both in terms of
ultimately the dollars you pay at the
end of the month like the order of
magnitude less than snowflake and also
like how it scales over time because
we want users to create as many tests as
possible catches more errors
gives more peace of mind and we don't
want to make it so that oh shoot you
know i only want to create these four
tests on these four important things but
i
if i create more than that then my costs
start exploding that's not what we want
at all so we try and make a model that
makes sense there
is that also something for the
data observability space that you also
give customers or tooling provides some
feedback on how you can reduce cost is
that something that will happen in the
future
you're laying out a roadmap we are
working on that it is a tricky problem
but it's something that we're actually
rolling out in beta right now is
analyzing the logs right the query logs
and analyzing the data that exists
and trying to suggest
both tables that aren't being used
and
could be deleted and the tables that are
being used frequently and could be
refactored but also identifying like
which
quarters are being run which are the
most expensive how can you
change your warehouse parameters to
optimize spend there there's a lot of
work for us to do in that direction and
we have all the metadata we need to do
it
we just have to like present it in the
right way this is other
job title which has
been around now for a few years but it
came up during this software
observability boom phase which is the
devops engineer
because if your data is not available
now you get a call like
midnight or whatever page of duty and
everything is
buzzing i'm assuming it's the same thing
for data observability are the new set
of jobs for people just doing this work
there's a new
i guess trend emerging called data ops
right that is an exact one-to-one
inspiration or copy of devops to the
data world there's an open question of
how big data can get within an
organization right like will there be
roughly as many people on the data team
as there are on the software engineering
teams
there's arguments for both yes and no
and i think that if data teams generally
don't become the size of software teams
that data ops as a job might be taken on
by existing rules
like data engineers analytics engineers
the heads of data of course but i think
at larger companies with sufficiently
large data teams we are seeing roles
emerge that kind of play the role of
data ops like
data platform managers right a data
product leads
data quality engineers
this is emerging but at the larger
companies and i've yet to see a smaller
companies
finally if i were to ask you to
summarize what is the biggest challenge
you see in the data observability space
and is there a magic bullet to solve it
the biggest challenge
is
extending data
quality beyond the data team
ultimately data
is produced
outside of the data team and is consumed
outside of the data team
and data teams themselves don't produce
any data right we call snowflake the
source of truth well frankly it's not
the source of any truth because
snowflake does not produce data
and
being able to extend
the visibility
that observability tools bring to data
teams but to the non-data teams i think
is a huge challenge because it bumps
into
questions of data literacy
like
does my cfo like if i say that the data
is not fresh do like do they know what
that means
or when a software engineer is perhaps
like making a change to an event name
and i was to say like this is the
downstream lineage like is that the
right way to say it so i think that is a
open question but ultimately where we
have to go because our goal here is
trust and the data needs to be trusted
by not only just the data team but
literally everyone within an
organization
for it to be used
interesting so trust is
so i'm hearing trust in the data as well
as maybe more learning on the
key terminologies
so that everybody speaking the same
language is what you're saying
definitely
meeting other people where they are and
not trying to you know bash them over
the head with terms that only make sense
to your discipline that's a difficult
problem
and it's a human problem like no one
tool can solve it it can only make it a
little bit easier
yeah this has been great chatting with
you kevin is there a place where
listeners can reach you is it on twitter
or is it on linkedin
yeah i'm kevin z e n g
h u kevin zung who
on twitter and linkedin you can also go
to metaplan.dev try it out or send me an
email kevin metaplan.dev i love talking
about all things data observability i
would love to hear your feedback great
i'll put this in the show notes and
can't thank you enough for coming on the
show kevin
it's been great having you
such a pleasure talking with you and
thank you for the wonderful questions
this is priyanka raghun for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter
or through our slack channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening